<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    STS-65
    Mission: International Microgravity Library (IML-2)
    Space Shuttle: Columbia
    Launch Pad: 39A
    Launched: July 8, 1994 at 12:43:00.069 p.m. EDT
    Landing Site: Kennedy Space Center, Florida
    Landing: July 23, 1994 at 6:38:00 a.m. EDT
    Mission Duration: 14 days, 17 hours, 55 minutes, 00 seconds
    Orbit Altitude: 160 nautical miles
    Orbit Inclination: 28.45 degrees
    
    Payload Specialist Chiaki Mukai became the first Japanese woman to fly in space; she also set the record for the longest flight to date by a female astronaut.
    
    STS-65 marked second flight of International Microgravity Laboratory (IML-2), carrying more than twice the number of experiments and facilities as IML-1. Crew split into two teams to perform around-the-clock research. More than 80 experiments, representing more than 200 scientists from six space agencies, were located in Spacelab module in payload bay (one piece of equipment stowed in middeck lockers). Fifty of the experiments delved into life sciences, including bioprocessing, space biology, human physiology and radiation biology. Some of the equipment used for these investigations had flown on previous Spacelab flights, such as European Space Agency's Biorack, making its third flight. IML-2 Biorack housed 19 experiments featuring chemicals and biological samples such as bacteria, mammalian and human cells, isolated tissues and eggs, sea urchin larvae, fruit flies and plant seedlings. Over the course of a single mission, specimens can evolve through several stages of life cycles, allowing study of effects of microgravity and cosmic radiation on living tissues.
    
    The flight marked the first time liftoff and reentry as experienced from the crew cabin were captured on videotape. Crew took time during mission to honor 25th anniversary of Apollo 11, noting it also featured a spacecraft named Columbia.
    
    Commander Robert D. Cabana, Pilot James D. Halsell Jr., Payload Commander Richard J. Hieb and Mission Specialists Carl E. Walz, Leroy Chiao and Donald A. Thomas and Payload Specialist Chiaki Naito-Mukai.
    
</xml>

